Hey, what's up guys? My name is Achono
and welcome back to my C++ series. So,
today we're going to be talking about
strings and specifically something
called small string optimization or SSO
for short. What does it mean? Why do we
care? And how does it improve our string
experience? Now, strings are a very
interesting topic, I think, in C++ or in
just in any language in general because
they have all of this kind of negative
stigma, I guess, associated with them.
They have this reputation of being slow.
And don't even start talking about
performance to a C++ programmer because
man, if something slow in C++
it's really easy to look at someone's
code, see them using strings in a way
that you just frown upon and then
immediately think that they're either
not a good programmer or they're doing
things the stupid slow way. There's just
so much negativity associated with
strings, believe me. But, I'm here to
tell you that it's not all bad and in
fact, sometimes when you do see someone
using a string
maybe it's not as bad as you think. Now,
strings in general, I think, are
something that we're just going to
continue talking about every now and
then on this channel. It's impossible to
program without strings, but on the
other hand, reducing your usage of
strings in your code can significantly
speed it up depending on how in fact you
do use them. So, expect this topic to
stay around. But, today specifically,
we're going to be looking at how small
strings are actually optimized by the
C++ standard library so that they end up
being not as bad as you think. But,
first I want to thank Hostinger for
sponsoring this video. If you guys have
not heard of Hostinger, Hostinger is a
fast and secure web hosting platform.
Now, I think that nowadays in 2020,
pretty much everyone should have a
website. If you don't have a website and
you're trying to become a programmer
well, you need some kind of website so
that you can easily show people what it
is you're working on and what you've
achieved, especially if you're looking
for a job. Don't even get me started on
that. And what people don't realize is
that the added benefit to all this is
that you will know how to set up a
website. The fact that you've got a
website on the internet, to me,
immediately means that, well, you know
how to set up a website. You know how
web hosting works, and that's a perk in
and of itself. Now, there's a lot to
love about Hostinger specifically. Apart
from being really, really fast, really
intuitive, the fact that they have
built-in diagnostics to help you along
the way if something like your DNS isn't
set up correctly. Apart from all of
that, they're also really, really
affordable, and I absolutely love that
because web hosting should be accessible
to as many people as possible, even if
you don't have a lot of money to spend
on this, and Hostinger, I really think
they hit the ball on that because they
are super amazing and affordable. A lot
of these kind of cheaper web hosts just
don't seem to do that great of a job,
but Hostinger is not some cheap web
host. Hostinger is it's just a really
good web hosting platform regardless of
the price. So, if you don't have a
website yet, and you want to get online,
or you're with some other web host, and
you're not enjoying that experience, and
you want to come over to a good one,
then definitely check out Hostinger.
There'll be a link in the description.
You can save up to 91% off their hosting
plans if you use this code, code Cherno.
So, definitely check out Hostinger if
you guys need any kind of web hosting.
Link in the description below.
All right. Strings. Strings, strings,
strings, strings, strings. Where would
we be without strings? Probably
not where we are today, whether that's a
good thing or a bad thing, don't know.
One of the reasons that we don't like
strings is because they tend to allocate
memory, and C++ heap allocations
bad. Those things are just grouped
together so much, even though
I mean, arguably speaking, memory
allocation maybe isn't that bad. Anyway,
I better not say anything cuz
So, because we know that creating a
standard string results in a memory
allocation,
a lot of people try and kind of avoid
that. They'll try and reduce their kind
of string usage or they'll try and come
up with creative ideas of how to use
strings or worst case scenario, they'll
just berate you for using strings
because why you allocating so much
memory all the time? Don't you know that
that is bad? But as I mentioned, I'm
here to tell you that no, it's not
necessarily bad because the C++ standard
library has, maybe somewhat
surprisingly, thought of this and
they've put a stop to it by saying that
small strings, that is strings that are
not exceedingly long,
they don't need to be heap allocated. I
can just allocate a little stack-based
buffer that is not heap allocated and
that is going to be my static string
storage for strings that are below a
certain length. Now, what that actual
length is to define a small string can
absolutely vary based on the C++
standard library that you're using, but
here in Visual Studio 2019, that length
seems to be 15 characters. If you have a
string that is 15 characters or less, it
will not allocate memory on the heap. It
will just use that stack buffer as I
mentioned. However, if you do have a
string that is 16 characters or above,
that's going to hit malloc and, you
know, heap alloc and whatever on earth
function is used to allocate memory on
whatever platform you're on. So, in
other words, if you have a string that's
quite small, you don't have to worry
about using a const char pointer or
trying to micromanage or optimize that
kind of bit of your code because likely
that's not going to result in a heap
allocation anyway. So, without further
ado, let's dive into Visual Studio and
actually take a look at how this works
behind the scenes and see it in action.
I'm just going to make a string. I'm
going to call it Shana. Now, this is a
really small string. It's only six
characters, which would throw a lot of
people off because if you assign this to
a standard string, there's this kind of
implication of a heap allocation. A lot
of people might choose to actually do
something like this, like a const char
name because this is something that is
clearly a static string, meaning we're
not going to be appending anything to
it. We're not taking it in from a file
or from like the console or anything
like that. It's just a simple static
string. So, why then would I use a
standard string if that comes with that
whole heap allocation overhead? Well,
here's the thing. It doesn't come with a
heap allocation overhead, because this
fits the criteria of a small string in
C++. Which means it will in fact just be
stored in a statically allocated buffer
that does not touch the heap at all. So,
let's take a look at this in action.
What I'm actually going to do is
something a little bit different instead
of just straight away jumping to a
practical example and then maybe taking
a look at, you know, overriding operator
new, which I think we will do eventually
in this video as well. I'm just going to
go to the definition of string. Now,
let's take a look at this. I'll hide
this solution explorer. So, we have
string as a basic string. Um now,
there's a few things that we need to
note here, mainly the fact that the
element type here is a char. So, if we
go to this class here and we take a look
at it, we have this element type here,
which we know is char. If we go down to
the constructor that actually takes in
some kind of buffer of characters, which
looks like what this thing is here. So,
we have this kind of const elem pointer,
and elem of course is a const char
pointer in this case. Now, some of this
stuff applies to only debug mode and
other stuff applies to release mode.
We'll take a look at that a bit later,
but the main function here is assign,
which takes in the actual pointer, being
that const char pointer, which is in
fact the word "Cherno" here, and then
also a count, which in this case would
be six, because Cherno is six
characters. If we go into this assign
function, it might be a little bit
difficult to find the right one, but in
this case it would be the one that takes
in that element. That of course
redirects to something else and does
some some extra conversion stuff, but if
we drill down even more and we find the
right one here, which is actually just a
little bit above here, you can see this
is the one that takes in that pointer
and then the count of how many
characters it is. there's this little if
statement here. And this basically says
that if the count, meaning the size of
the string, is below a certain value,
which is this kind of reserved size,
which we'll check out in a minute, then
actually what happens is we simply get
what looks like to be an already
existing buffer of memory and simply
move our characters over into that
buffer of memory and that's it. And then
we just return it. So there's no
allocation at all. Whereas here, in this
case, if it doesn't pass this if
statement test, we actually call this
reallocate four function, which as you
can see eventually over here actually
calls an allocate function. And that
allocate function will in fact hit the
new operator and will cause a heap
allocation. So let's go back a little
bit here. What is this my res variable?
It's the current storage reserved for
string. So in other words, it's just
that reserved size. So anything below
this or equal to this will constitute a
small string. And if we take a look at
where this is actually set inside here,
you can see that it gets set to buffer
size minus one. And buffer size for us
is this scary val buff size, which is in
fact a constant expression. And in this
case, it's actually going to be 16. And
we eventually subtract one, so we have
15. Meaning 15 is that maximum amount of
characters that constitutes a small
string. So that's kind of all the code
and just a little bit kind of looking at
how everything works here. And if I go
back to that assign function, whichever
one it is, then you can see that the
presence of this if statement does in
fact result in no heap allocations for a
string that is 15 characters or smaller.
And we can of course test this out. So
what I like doing is writing this little
operator new here. We'll just take in
the size here. This will just simply
return a malloc with the right size
here. The benefit here is that we can
actually put a breakpoint and I'll also
add some custom code here to actually
print this. So we'll just say allocating
and then size and then bytes here. Okay,
so let's not worry about this. Let's put
a uh c in dot get so that we don't close
our console and then let's launch this.
All right, so check this out. We
actually allocate eight bytes even
though our string clearly is below 15
characters. That's another little quirk
with Visual Studio string class. It's
basically something that only happens in
debug mode, but if we switch to release
mode and we launch this, then you'll see
we have no allocations at all. But if I
expand this and make this a little bit
more than these six characters, so 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 14 15. So that's exactly 15
characters. Let's take a look at that.
Still nothing, no allocations. But the
moment I go into 16 characters, you can
see we allocate 32 bytes. So it
immediately snaps up to this predefined
value here. With just one character
less, we have absolutely no heap
allocations, but once we tip over to 16
characters or more, we allocate memory
on the heap. And that's basically all
there is to say for this video. If you
don't care about any more details, you
can pretty much stop watching now. Just
know that in C++ and specifically in
this implementation of the C++ standard
library, which I'm using Visual Studio
2019 here, any string that is 15
characters or less does not cause a heap
allocation and in that sense it's an
optimization. It's more efficient. It's
faster. Now, let's quickly take a look
at what on earth happens in debug mode
that causes an allocation. We'll put a
breakpoint here and I'll also take this
back to Cherno and we'll check it out.
All right, so this allocation comes from
external code. Let's just show that
external code and let's go up to here,
which is probably going to show us what
we want to see. I'll just make some more
room here. There it is, container proxy
pointer. So this is what causes the
allocation. Now this container proxy
pointer, you can see is equal to this
rebind Alec T situation, which is
actually a template argument for this uh
class or I don't even know what this is
to be honest. It's so complicated, but
basically the point of this whole thing
is that you can see that this is only
the case if the iterator debug level is
not zero because in that sense, this
part of the code gets compiled. However,
if the debug level is zero, which is
what it would be in release mode, you
can see that instead this get proxy
allocator is a fake allocator and this
fake allocator does absolutely nothing.
So, this container proxy 12, which
eventually actually causes that new
allocation to take place. So, it turns
out that it's a little bit of a red
herring in the sense that it's a debug
only allocation and it's not in fact
small string optimization not working.
It's just the case for all debug
strings. Okay, so that's small string
optimization. Strings that are
sufficiently small will not cause any
heap allocations and thus will result in
your program running faster. It's a cute
little trick they've worked into the C++
standard library to make it that little
bit faster. How thoughtful. Anyway, I
hope you guys enjoyed this video. If you
did, please hit that like button. Drop a
comment below with what you would like
to see next. I'm about to come out with
a whole bunch of like data structures
and patterns and all of that kind of
stuff videos. That's what I'm kind of
more or less gravitating towards with
the C++ series. Don't forget to check
out Hostinger for up to 91% off web
hosting and I will see you guys next
time. Goodbye.